   
   
   <section title="TimeSlotted Channel Hopping">

   The IEEE802.15.4 Task Group has been driving the development
of low-power low-cost radio technology. The Timeslotted
Channel Hopping mode, added to the 2015 revision of
the IEEE802.15.4 standard, is targeted at the embedded and
industrial world, where reliability, energy consumption and
cost drive the application space.
The IEEE802.15.4 physical layer has been designed to
support demanding low-power scenarios targeting the use of
unlicensed bands, both the 2.4 GHz and sub GHz Industrial,
Scientific and Medical (ISM) bands. This has imposed requirements
in terms of frame size, data rate and bandwidth
to achieve reduced collision probability, reduced packet error
rate, and acceptable range with limited transmission power.
The PHY layer supports frames of up to 127 bytes. The
Medium Access Control (MAC) sublayer overhead is in the
order of 10-20 bytes, leaving about 100 bytes to the upper
layers. IEEE802.15.4 uses spread spectrum modulation such
as the Direct Sequence Spread Spectrum (DSSS).

As the core technique in IEEE802.15.4, TSCH splits time
in multiple time slots that repeat over time. The structure is referred
as a Slotframe. For each timeslot, a set of available frequencies
can be used, resulting in a matrix-like schedule (see Fig. <xref target="fig_slotframe"/>). 


<figure title="Slotframe example with scheduled cells between nodes A, B and C"       anchor="fig_slotframe">
<artwork><![CDATA[
                       timeslot offset
     | 0    1    2    3    4  | 0    1    2    3    4  |    Nodes
     +------------------------+------------------------+   +-----+
     |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |   |  C  |
CH-1 | EB |    |    |C->B|    | EB |    |    |C->B|    |   |     |
     |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |   +-----+
     +-------------------------------------------------+      |
     |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |      |
CH-2 |    |    |B->C|    |B->A|    |    |B->C|    |B->A|   +-----+
     |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |   |  B  |
     +-------------------------------------------------+   |     |
 ...                                                       +-----+  
                                                              |
     +-------------------------------------------------+      |
     |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |   +-----+     
CH-15|    |A->B|    |    |    |    |A->B|    |    |    |   |  A  |
     |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |    |   |     |
     +-------------------------------------------------+   +-----+ 
ch.
offset                                                           
]]></artwork> 
            </figure>

This schedule represents the possible communications
of a node with its neighbors, and is managed by a Scheduling
Function such as The Minimal Scheduling Function (MSF) <!-- cite MSF draft -->. Each cell in the schedule
is identified by its slotoffset and channeloffset coordinates. A
cell's timeslot offset indicates its position in time, relative to the
beginning of the slotframe. A cell's channel offset is an index
which maps to a frequency at each iteration of the slotframe.
Each packet exchanged between neighbors happens within one
cell. An Absolute Slot Number (ASN) indicates the number
of slots elapsed since the network started. It increments at
every slot. This is a 5 byte counter that can support networks
running for more than 300 years without wrapping (assuming
a 10 ms timeslot). Channel hopping provides increased reliability
to multi-path fading and external interference.
It is handled by TSCH through a channel hopping sequence
referred as macHopSeq in the IEEE802.15.4 specification.    
   
   <section title="Provenance and Documents">
   
   </section><!-- Provenance and Documents   -->
   
   <section title="General Characteristics">
   
   </section><!-- General Characteristics  -->
   
   <section title="Applicability to Deterministic Flows">
   
   </section><!-- Applicability to deterministic flows  -->
   
   </section><!-- title="tech X" -->
   
   